One. Four, five. Fourteen.
Para con la prensa. La voy a predecir, ¿verdad? Estos formaron un libro, pero cuando, y los mandó a imprimir, Américo. Pero cuando ya creció más, vio lo que él creía que era error. Entonces, nosotros vivíamos desde hace tiempo en la calle Madison, West Madison. Nos trajo una caja grandota, llena.
Le dijo a la esposa mía que quería que se los guardáramos allí hasta que no tuviera tiempo de volver porque estaba en [inaudible], porque quería destruirlos. Mi esposa sacó como 10 o 15 y los escondió. Yo me quedé con uno, los demás yo creo que un hermano mío se ha llevado uno y el otro también.
De una manera una copia cayó en manos de Jesse Sloss y él me platicó que la tenía.
Fíjese. Yo creo que él falleció, yo creo.
¿Ya falleció? ¿Estaba enfermo?
Sí. Yo creo que sí. No sé cuándo, pero yo oí mencionar un señor que trabajaba con él. Joe Rivera me dijo que, el county treasurer. .
Estaba enfermo de los pies.
Si, si.
Yo lo vi a él en el mall, a el y a la esposa. Estaba casado con Tencha. Creo que se llamaba Tencha Hinojosa. Pero no sabía que se había muerto.
Yo creo que sí. Parece que sí. Yo me informo, pero yo creo que sí.
Él me platicó que tenía una copia. Como digo, yo tengo una aquí, pero no hallo si prestar, si permitirles que tomen una foto de la foto que está ahí- porque según Américo no le gustó ya cuando creció. Le daba vergüenza que leyeran aquellos versos de un muchacho enamorado.
Quería destruir todo, pero yo me quedé con uno. Lo tengo ahí. No hallo si permitirte que tomes una foto de esa foto. Porque es grande.
Si va haber problema, nomás las fotos que nos permite eso está bien. Porque no queremos que se disguste usted con él.
Sí, porque si te permito Te lo voy a enseñar, pero no quiero que tomes una fotografía porque no quiero ninguna controversia. No quiero que se vaya a enojar aquel y todo eso.
Nosotros tampoco. Mejor si no quiere enseñármelo ni quiero verlo, así no hay problema. Nomás nos permite lo que
Las que tengo, ahí Las fotografía que tengo ahí ahorita te las enseño. Mercedes!
Yo se los traigo. Aquí está en la mesa. ¿Se los traigo?
Ah pues, tráemelo.
Sí. Está bien.
Tienen un papelito, mire, está ahí. Está con sus hijos y está ahí el papelito, que es este.
Muy bien. Gracias. Ahorita empezamos, Noro, cuando estés listo.
Sí. Este. Ese que no es de color.
¿Qué es ese retrato?
Es un señor y tres niños.
¿Es Américo?
Sí. Es Américo. Dice, "Enero 1960".
¿1900 qué?
60.
En la navidad. Dice, "Navidad 59". Sí, será Doctor Paredes.
¿Es él y dos niños?
Sí. Los tres niños. Los dos niños, uno grande y uno está en los brazos de él, chiquito, y otro.
¿Hay otros que Lydia los buscó y están ahí?
Sí. Aquí están marcados. Muy bien.
Este, Mercedes? [Mercedes- Sí.] Tráeme el libro. Las poesías. [Mercedes- Okay]
¿Estos sí sabe que usted los tiene y no hay problema verdad, de hacerle copias?
¿Qué?
Digo.
¿Esto? sí.
Sí. Está bien.
Estos son retratos que tomó con la familia.
Está bien.
Lo que te voy a enseñar es viene en el libro ¿Ese es el retrato?
Sí.
Es cuando estaba joven.
Fíjese. Mire look at this picture, it's great. You can't take it pero-
[Traducción: Mire esta foto, esta genial. No te le puedes llevar pero-]
Alguna poesía, que estaban alguna de ellas, no tiene la fecha.
Sí. A ver. [Sonido: Vidrio quiebra afuera de pantalla]
¿Qué pasó? ¿Se quebró algo?
Aquí dice, 3/1/36.
¿36?
Aquí tiene los datos del año, el mes y el día que escribió la poesía.
¿Dice que el 36?
Sí. 36.
Ya tenía 21 años.
¿Él tenía 21 años?
Sí. Porque él nació el 15 y 10. 15 y 10, 25 y 5 son 30. Son 15 y 6, 21. Tenía 21 años. Estaba jovencito.
Mire, sí. Usted tiene unas pocas copias, ¿verdad, esta es son unas de las cuantas copias que hay?
Es la única que yo sé. Yo creo que había una en el Texas Southmost College Library, pero no sé quién la vio allí.
Yolanda González debería saber si está ahí.
¿Qué- Yolanda González?
Yolanda González. Ella debería saber si está ahí o no.
Ella debe saber. Se llama ¿Qué dice?
Cantos adolescentes. Pueden conseguirlo allí. Creo que esté allí.
Está bien. Yo le pregunto al doctor para ver si nos permite poderlo usar.
Sí.
Don Américo y tres niños en la navidad. Está en blanco y negro.
¿Bueno, quieren tomar ese? ¿Quieren ese? Fíjese los demás que están ahí.
Sí. Aquí está uno. Doctor Paredes y no sé quién es este señor con lentes y dos niños. ¿Será la señora de él?
Sí.
¿Este es la señora de él y dos de los niños?
Será.
Aquí está uno yo creo que con usted. Son cinco hombres. Este a la izquierda, no sé si es su papá o quién será.
¿Hay cinco hombres?
Sí, hay cinco hombres. Tres están en un sofá, y dos están sentados adelante.
¿Están en una casa, en una residencia?
En una casa. Hay un cuadro detrás.
Ah entonces son los- Yo tenía dos hermanos que eran cuates. Amador y Eleazar, y Américo eran tres. Eliseo eran cuatro y yo son cinco. Solamente séra nosotros.
Pues hay cinco, hay cinco
¿Hay cinco hombres?
Sí, el señor del medio tiene unos lentes oscuros.
Debe ser Eliseo, mi hermano. El mayor.
¿Usted está al lado derecho? Trae una corbata. Del lado izquierdo Don Paredes y sus hermanos aquí. ¿Cómo se llamaban los cuates?
Amador y Eleazar. Eran gemelos. Amador fue principal del Annie S. Putegnat.
Sí, es verdad.
Annie S. Putegnat. Se murió cuando era principal ahí. Fue principal por 27 años allí.
¿No tiene fotos de Don Paredes cuando estaban en el military, en el ejército?
¿De quién?
De Don Américo cuando estaba en el ejército.
Verás que sí tengo. Tenía, pero no lo encontró la hija mía. Tenía uno donde estaba parado, uniformado con pantalones largos. Está solo, pero no lo encuentro.
No lo encuentra. Está bien. Aquí hay uno yo creo que cuando graduó de Texas. En junio 1956.
Sí, doctor degree. Is the 1956, ¿verdad?
1956, right.
Bueno, esa puedes tomar.
He is in the center. You've got, I guess, a whole family there, or most of the family.
[Traducción: Está en el centro, supongo que ahí tienes toda la familia, o casi toda la familia.]
Sí, está mamá, está la esposa mía, la esposa de Amador y ahí está Amador también.
Sí, está Amador.
Está Amador y está Ofelia. Está Herman [inaudible] que era el principal del Pace High School . La esposa de él también está ahí. Yo y la esposa mía. Mamá y Américo con el cap and gown.
Sí, he's got the cap and gown.
Puedes tomar esta también si quieres.
Está bien. Ahorita nos da la información de ellos y él nos toma las fotos acá individual.
¿Traen la cámara?
Sí. Ahí traemos la cámara. Hay un foto aquí que dice 1944.
Es Américo.
Es un grupo de niños. Parece que están en la escuela. Hay varios aquí. No sé si uno de ustedes está aquí.
Si no está marcado con el papel yo creo que no es Américo.
No está. Está bien.
Lydia fue la que- Como yo no veo, la señora Olivares que está aquí apenas tiene tres años de estar con nosotros, no conoce a toda la familia. Américo, yo creo que no lo ha visto. Nunca lo ha visto. Porque todo el tiempo está enfermo, casi la mayor parte. Viene poco para acá.
¿Marcó alguno de los tres o cuatro fotos?
Los marcó con papelitos que tenía. Ahí están todavía los papeles.
Sí, ¿son los únicos que quiere que tomemos?
Sí, esos son los que encontró ella.
Está bien... Aquí está una señora que se llama Liliana Longoria Garza o Diana Longoria Garza.
¿Cómo se llama?
Diana Longoria Garza.
¿El primer nombre?
No puedo ver porque tiene un pedazo- Es Juana Longoria Garza.
Ese suena a Juanita, es la suegra mía.
Está bien.
Es señora vieja ya, ¿verdad? Sí.
¿Está sentado? Sí, está sentado. Creo que al lado de la carretera.
¿No tiene fecha ni nada?
Nada. No tiene.
No sé quién sería.
¿No tiene otros libros que? Yo tengo varios que escribió Don Américo. Algunos, por ejemplo, invitaciones de graduación o algo así que
Hombres, yo creo que sí, pero te voy a decir que me tomaría un mes.
Sí, ¿a buscarlos?
Sí, porque son tantas las cosas que tenemos aquí.
Sí, yo entiendo. Está bien. ¿Ya va a cumplir 80?
Américo tiene 76. Él nació el 15. Sí, ya va a cumplir 80, ¿verdad?
Sí va a cumplir 80.
El 95 cumplo los 80 en septiembre. En este septiembre. El año 95 cumplo 80. Apenas el 15, 80, 95. Cumple 80, él ya tiene 79.
¿Usted asistió a la escuela aquí en Brownsville?
¿Quién? ¿Qué tiene?
Usted. ¿Fue a la escuela aquí en Brownsville?
Sí.
¿Cuándo graduó usted?
Yo no gradué el high school aquí. Tomé un examen hace muchos años y lo pasé. El profesor que estaba allí, sería el dean, se llamaba Philips. ¿Estará allí todavía?
No, no está allí. Sí. Yo-
¿Lo viste meter? Philips.
Si, yo trabaje con el.
Quería que me registrara para- No, le dije. Ya estoy, fue ahora verás el Yo creo que fue como 60.
Por ahí. Porque me fui para el Hammond. Yo tenía mucha experiencia y había leído, estaba trabajando, había trabajado en una oficina de Abstract? Company y tenía mucho experiencia y práctica en la lectura y la interpretación de documentos legales y la preparación de documentos legales.
A fuerza, no a fuerzas, ¿verdad? Pero me gustaba el trabajo. Aprendí fórmulas geométricas, cómo sacar el length of a hypotenuse, sacar el volume del cylinder, cubic inches y cosas de esas aprendía ahí en el trabajo. Las aprendía nomás porque me gustaba. Tengo un libro que, te voy a decir la verdad,
nunca lo estudié, lo traté de leer ya cuando tenía la vista mala. Fue un texto de escuela de un tío mío que se llamaba José María Manzano que nació en Bagdad, pero no Baghdad en Iraq. No, Bagdad aquí en el río. En la boca del río. Bagdad aquí en la boca del río.
Estaba en la escuela él allí y allí aprendió, tenía una torre hecha de madera donde tenía el telégrafo cuando estaba chico él. Ese telégrafo tenía dos alambres, mandaban cuando llegaba un barco y se paraba allá lejos, porque no había puerto ahí. No había entrada para buques.
Venía un barco y llegaba allá lejos con un anteojo le veían el nombre. Telegrafiaban a Matamoros y allá en la oficina del telégrafo les avisaba a los comerciantes en Matamoros que había llegado un barco, dos barcos, tres barcos, de tal parte. El nombre.
Se dejaban ir desde aquí en carretas y en guayines y caballos a levantar la mercancía. Porque traían mercancía de Europa. Aquí en Brownsville no era [inaudible]. Mi tío José allí nació, ahí vivió, fue a la escuela y dejó ese librito, yo lo tengo. Tiene más de 100 años. Fíjese.
Ahorita lo traigo. Mercedes. A ver si me olle. ¿Mercedes?
Está bien. ¿Mercedes, Mercedes?
Sí.
Mercedes, tú sabes dónde está, allí en el cajón. Yo creo que está en el cajón del medio del peinador.
Hay un sobre grande. Hay dos sobres, en uno de ellos está otro sobre donde tengo el librito que se llama Elementos de Geometría.
¿Quiere que se lo traiga?
Tráemelo. Hay otras cosas ahí también. Ahí está el documento para Pedro.
Sí.
Mi abuelo- Se crió, nació aquí. El papá de él se llamaba Leandro Paredes. Tenía vacas y caballos, yeguas. Ahí donde, así se llamaba en ese tiempo también. Se llama todavía La Parra Ranch. ¿La has oído mentar?
Sí, la he oído mentar.
Que está enfrentito donde dice Sarita. Porque Sarita, la Sarita Kennedy, era hija de Don Gregorio, que Don Gregorio era hijo de Mifflin, el dueño de todo el rancho ese, La Parra. Mi papá Leandro antes de que viniera Mifflin Kennedy le rentó primero y luego le compró a una heredera,
una señora que se llamaba Loreto Villarreal de Capdevielle. Le compró el derecho que tenía en dos agostaderos, el agostadero La Parra y el agostadero de El Infiernillo. Que está pegado, la Parra pega al arroyo Los Olmos que es ahí donde está Sarita. Está Riviera. El arroyo Los Olmos.
El otro agostadero se llama El Infiernillo ahí donde está el Riviera. Ahí compró papá Leandro lo que le llamaban a él, le decían un derecho, y compró La Parra también. Ándele, este es.
¿El libro que dijo?
Sí. Aquí está.
Mire.
Te fijas en las fechas, 1887 y está escrito en una de las páginas del Jose. Dice, "JM Manzano". Manzano. Sí. Aquí dice Bagdad. Bagdad, 1887. 87.
Sí. Aquí dice.
Era el texto de geometría y en México y ya pa cuando estaban en el libro cuarto, quinto ya tomaban geometría.
Sí. [Risa]
Y aquí no. [Risa]
No aquí hasta nueve o diez. [inaudible]
¿Te fijaste en la pasta, en la inscripción?  JM Manzano, dice.
Sí, JM Manzano. Bagdad.
[ Una foto en color de Americo Paredes con sus dos hijos y su esposa sentados con un pastel de cumpleaños.]
Bagdad. En el colegio San José estuve ¿Mercedes? [El video se corta a negro]
I could fill the heel of your boot academically because-
Boy, the battery of this came out.
No, I say that I hope that one day I can fill the heel of your boot academically. [laughter]
Oh, come on.
I've written some short stories and stuff, remember that I promised to send you and I brought them to you Tio, so you could read at your leisure. Some poesías, de pos, you know my mother was always quoting Longfellow and "learn to labor and to wait" and-- Who was the other one?
¿cómo se llamaba el "We are architects of fate working within these walls of time"?
She loved Longfellow.
She loved Longfellow and she really instilled- [video cut]
Back to something you asked me, why did I work so hard to get an education? When I finished high school the prospects I had then was working at a shoe store, or a dry good store selling shoes, and I hated that, and it certainly did not lead anywhere. I got the chance
to go two years at college and, of course, that flooded my appetite. I knew that most of my other school mates went on to get a degree. The best I could do was get a job at the Brownsville Herald making $11.40 a week and even though at that time that was a little more than is today,
it wasn't very much. [coughs] In 1940 when things got really- when the the war really got started in, in Europe. Pan American Airways started arming planes for Great Britain. I got a job there at $15 a week but I was still at that time the Brownsville Herald and The Monitor of McAllen, and the Morning Star
were bought all by a man named Hubert Hudson and all became-- They continued to publish separately but this Sunday paper was done in Brownsville and was for all of them. I still had a job there Saturdays and Sundays, I wrote a great deal for the Brownsville Herald.
In fact, a lot of the articles I wrote on Mexican culture that were used in the early Charros Days were cannibalized and printed, and reprinted later. My salary rose to about $15, I was getting $15 over there, and at that time [coughs] I got a job singing my own songs on the radio that I was paid
the magnificent sum-- I loved to mention that, $1 a minute for 15 minutes a week, so I really was making for what people like me would make at that time- a lot of money, $45 a week. Though inflation was on, I still felt that I was at a dead end. So this is something that some people thought
I was crazy to do because the job I had at with PanAm was a war job, therefore I was exempt from the draft. There were a number of reasons, including the fact that some of my friends, Matías Serrata, who played the guitar with me, was killed in France. Este muchacho, se me olvida el nombre, [Translation: That man, I forget his name.]
Miguel Morán, died after action in Attu, and I began to get a guilt feeling but also I want to get out of Brownsville because it was a dead end as far as education was concerned. I just quit the job with Pan American and I could not volunteer because at that time this was in '44 already,
they didn't want people in the Navy, they didn't want people in the Air Force, they wanted people with rifles. They weren't called grunts at that time but that was what they wanted so they told me, "Go home, we'll call you," and I worked with The Herald full-time for a living, they took me.
In a way it was very good for me because somebody who had been reading too many detective books saw that I was a newspaper reporter and they put me in the CID, the civil, or Criminal Investigation Division. Now, those were supposed to be detectives. There was one other reporter from California,
all the rest were former highway patrolmen, detectives, and we were supposed to be trained in law enforcement. Of course, I washed out on that, and so at that time they sent me to Seattle, and at that time the war ended anyway, so by the time I ended up in Japan, in Nagoya, the war was over.
Again, a lucky break, they were starting a newspaper in the base, the replacement center, and there were several people there. There were two men, one from New York, one from San Francisco, both of them are Jewish extraction, both of them Left-wing radicals hasta las cachas, [Translation: up to their necks.]
one of them was a member of the Communist Party. They were looking over, they saw my name, and they had read a book by Hart Stilwell, he had been my editor who had read my book. He had not been offended by what I say in the novel about the Rangers,
his father was a Texas ranger, but he was enraged about what I said about Dobie. We fell out on that, he said, "The old man would do anything you wanted to," "Yes, Massa would do anything for me, wouldn't he?" So we had a falling out on that and he never was interested in that.
He published a book called Border City in which he was a radical reporter very much like me, in it. These people went to see whom they could pick to work in the paper and they asked me where I was from, I said, "Brownsville," and they said, "Have you heard of a book named Border City ?"
"Well i'm in it" I told them. They hire for the newspaper and the group there were all people with college education. A man that became a very close friend of mine until he died just recently in Germany. Horst de la Croix, he already had a masters, the others had at least a bachelor's, so I was in a group
that really helped me orient myself there, and I stayed after, they only kept me for another year. In 1946 I was discharged, but I got a job over there with the international branch of American Red Cross. Not the International Red Cross but the American Red Cross,
they had an international branch that work with Red Cross Societies, especially Japanese, Korean, and Chinese. I spent a year in China going around as PRO for China, and then I was in Korea, and that really broadened my horizons. When Red Cross, to use a current word, downsized,
I no longer had a job. I got a job editing a little magazine for the armed forces for two years. During that time I read a lot the section in which this magazine was also was part of the armed forces college so I took classes in the armed forces college
because I realized I didn't want to go back to Brownsville with just a junior college education, it wasn't anything for me to do that I would want to do. So I took a gamble and came to UT and I got the bachelor's and found that, of course, I was much better read than most of my fellow students.
After all, I was 35 years old, I was older than most graduate students as far as it went, so I did very well. I got what I had wanted at the time, an education, because it's necessary if you're going to really-- Let's put it in [inaudible] terms, to have a good income. [laughs]
Yes, the word heritage is synonymous with your work as a folklorist, as an activist.
Pardon?
The word heritage is synonymous with you, Dr. Paredes, as a folklorist, as an activist, as a scholar. Why is one's heritage so important?
That comes back to my early days when I used to listen to the old man talk and then I would spend three months over there, and then I would come, and take history, which told us a completely different view. I remember arguing with my teacher about the Monroe doctrine, some of those things
I got in there, because she felt that it was something very good for Latin America. I told her no, and she totally was-- I have it verbatim in the novel, she said, "What if you have a situation in which there's a little boy with candy and then a big boy comes
and tries to take the candy away from him, then another big boy comes and pushes the big boy away?" I said, "Yes, but then the other big boy takes the candy away from the little boy," and of course she allowed those things.
What we knew in our hearts from what our elders told us was different, that our heritage was not being given the respect that it deserved. What I did in The Herald during the Charro Days was milder, showing this song, for example, most Anglos I knew thought
that Sobre Las Olas was a German waltz, they knew it as Over The Waves. I wrote an article about Juventino Rosas and now he had written it and a number of other songs, so those things. But, more important to me was to try show what had been done, the injustices that have been done to our people,
and the value of our heritage. Much of that fell on deaf ears until I finally was able to come here and first I had almost forgotten the Nahuatl so what I did was with With His Pistol in His Hand was do the same job from a non-fiction viewpoint and using Gregorio Cortéz as a major figure in it.
I was not the only one on that, there were people working on that, even the LULAC at the time it was very timid, very assimilationist, yet they would come out once in a while. One of my younger brothers, Eleazar, he's dead now, he took a course-- And that was later, I never had that happen to me,
where he was told that, rather a textbook, said that Mexicans lived under trees and he had a big fight with the teacher, and he was expelled from school. One of my older brother went to see the LULAC people and they straightened the matter out, so that was happening all along.
The thing was that most of what our people knew was in corridos and in legends, in oral history, and I wanted to bring those things to the majority because I felt there were enough people of good will among the Anglos who if they saw our side they would really react. In a talk I gave
at Sacramento state after George Sánchez died, there was an activist. I made that point because Edward Simmons who did do a great deal, he was one of those that awakened, did say in his book The Chicano: From Caricature to Self-Portrait he says, "The lazy bandido sleeping
against the adobe wall finally has awakened," and I challenged him on that saying that we had been awake. People had been writing in Spanish mostly, that was the problem, so few of our elders knew English. They'd been writing, another one was Alonso Perales, En defensa de mi raza,
and they had been organizing and very often being put down, sometimes violently because of that. What I said there was the people that had awakened to a new ear were the Anglos because it was about that time that Anglos of good will began to see our side and we needed their help
to be able to make ourselves heard. That's why this story "The Hammon and the Beans" got published by an Anglo of good will, Ronnie Dugger, after a lot of Anglos refused to see that there was anything in it. We were lucky in a sense, I was, the English department has always been liberal, and Texas-
and they were willing to listen to me and even to allow me to get a PhD in English which was written about a ballad in Spanish about a historical figure. Chicanos very often don't know where to place me, whether to say I'm a historian, or I'm an anthropologist, or a literary figure,
but With His Pistol in His Hand had all of those things. I don't think I could have done that, at that time in the '50s, at any other department. Perhaps in anthropology because the anthropology have always been-- I didn't even know the anthropology department existed at that time.
What kind of comments can you make to children about their abuelitos and abuelitas? Why is it so important for children to still communicate with them? Sometimes you know in modern times with so much technology we forget where part of our history is, and part of our history is in our family.
Why is it so important for them to communicate?
One of my dreams, I never fulfilled it, though there's some people that were working on it, Tony, and do you know Joe Graham?
Yes, very well, we worked together.
Yes, he got his- [video cuts to black]
- our people put documents, things they had written, books they had read, all of those things went to the castaña and I wanted my students to go and talk to their abuelitos and abuelitas, to see about what they had, and to give them to their teachers who were interested in this sort of thing,
and that has been done to some extent. Not only does it further the knowledge our people but it gives the student self-esteem, to know that just because their grandparents don't know much English, or don't know any English at all, that they're dumb.
They probably were writing décimas, or other kind of poetry, and nobody knows about it, so that I think going back to one's roots is very important.
You founded the Mexican-American Studies Department here?
Yes.
How did you feel when you became the first one that ever creates such a department?
There we had a lot of problems. They tried. We had a Dean here who was supposed to be a liberal, the only liberal thing about him was that that he hated Frank Erwin who was a member of the Board of Regents, his name was--
John Silber.
Silber, old long John Silver they called him. [laughter] He was a short man.
[laughs] Carajo.
He was a son of a bitch. [laughs]
No doubt about it, he was as racist as he could be but most of the Anglo people thought he was a liberal. After all, he was locking horns with Frank Irwin, and Frank Irwin was no raging liberal himself, obviously. He tried to hamstring this thing by pitting the blacks against us. He took charge
because he scared the administration by telling that if we didn't have an ethnic studies program immediately they would be burning in the streets, and so on. He took charge and he established a program of ethnic studies, not Mexican-American studies, not Black studies,
and he got a retired, old retired professor, a black professor to run it. Of course, he thought that he had been given the job of setting up Black studies, so I had to clash with him. For example, he wanted the program to have Swahili, all students had to learn Swahili, but Swahili was never
an African language, it was a lengua franca that the Arabs developed when they were doing slaving expeditions in east Africa. He opposed my wanting to have Spanish--[Video cuts to black]
I could fill the heel of your boot academically because-
Boy, the battery of this came out.
No, I say that I hope that one day I can fill the heel of your boot academically. [laughter]
Oh, come on.
I've written some short stories and stuff, remember that I promised to send you and I brought them to you Tio, so you could read at your leisure. Some poesías, de pos, you know my mother was always quoting Longfellow and "learn to labor and to wait" and-- Who was the other one?
¿cómo se llamaba el "We are architects of fate working within these walls of time"?
She loved Longfellow.
She loved Longfellow and she really instilled- [video cut]
Back to something you asked me, why did I work so hard to get an education? When I finished high school the prospects I had then was working at a shoe store, or a dry good store selling shoes, and I hated that, and it certainly did not lead anywhere. I got the chance
to go two years at college and, of course, that flooded my appetite. I knew that most of my other school mates went on to get a degree. The best I could do was get a job at the Brownsville Herald making $11.40 a week and even though at that time that was a little more than is today,
it wasn't very much. [coughs] In 1940 when things got really- when the the war really got started in, in Europe. Pan American Airways started arming planes for Great Britain. I got a job there at $15 a week but I was still at that time the Brownsville Herald and The Monitor of McAllen, and the Morning Star
were bought all by a man named Hubert Hudson and all became-- They continued to publish separately but this Sunday paper was done in Brownsville and was for all of them. I still had a job there Saturdays and Sundays, I wrote a great deal for the Brownsville Herald.
In fact, a lot of the articles I wrote on Mexican culture that were used in the early Charros Days were cannibalized and printed, and reprinted later. My salary rose to about $15, I was getting $15 over there, and at that time [coughs] I got a job singing my own songs on the radio that I was paid
the magnificent sum-- I loved to mention that, $1 a minute for 15 minutes a week, so I really was making for what people like me would make at that time- a lot of money, $45 a week. Though inflation was on, I still felt that I was at a dead end. So this is something that some people thought
I was crazy to do because the job I had at with PanAm was a war job, therefore I was exempt from the draft. There were a number of reasons, including the fact that some of my friends, Matías Serrata, who played the guitar with me, was killed in France. Este muchacho, se me olvida el nombre, [Translation: That man, I forget his name.]
Miguel Morán, died after action in Attu, and I began to get a guilt feeling but also I want to get out of Brownsville because it was a dead end as far as education was concerned. I just quit the job with Pan American and I could not volunteer because at that time this was in '44 already,
they didn't want people in the Navy, they didn't want people in the Air Force, they wanted people with rifles. They weren't called grunts at that time but that was what they wanted so they told me, "Go home, we'll call you," and I worked with The Herald full-time for a living, they took me.
In a way it was very good for me because somebody who had been reading too many detective books saw that I was a newspaper reporter and they put me in the CID, the civil, or Criminal Investigation Division. Now, those were supposed to be detectives. There was one other reporter from California,
all the rest were former highway patrolmen, detectives, and we were supposed to be trained in law enforcement. Of course, I washed out on that, and so at that time they sent me to Seattle, and at that time the war ended anyway, so by the time I ended up in Japan, in Nagoya, the war was over.
Again, a lucky break, they were starting a newspaper in the base, the replacement center, and there were several people there. There were two men, one from New York, one from San Francisco, both of them are Jewish extraction, both of them Left-wing radicals hasta las cachas, [Translation: up to their necks.]
one of them was a member of the Communist Party. They were looking over, they saw my name, and they had read a book by Hart Stilwell, he had been my editor who had read my book. He had not been offended by what I say in the novel about the Rangers,
his father was a Texas ranger, but he was enraged about what I said about Dobie. We fell out on that, he said, "The old man would do anything you wanted to," "Yes, Massa would do anything for me, wouldn't he?" So we had a falling out on that and he never was interested in that.
He published a book called Border City in which he was a radical reporter very much like me, in it. These people went to see whom they could pick to work in the paper and they asked me where I was from, I said, "Brownsville," and they said, "Have you heard of a book named Border City ?"
"Well i'm in it" I told them. They hire for the newspaper and the group there were all people with college education. A man that became a very close friend of mine until he died just recently in Germany. Horst de la Croix, he already had a masters, the others had at least a bachelor's, so I was in a group
that really helped me orient myself there, and I stayed after, they only kept me for another year. In 1946 I was discharged, but I got a job over there with the international branch of American Red Cross. Not the International Red Cross but the American Red Cross,
they had an international branch that work with Red Cross Societies, especially Japanese, Korean, and Chinese. I spent a year in China going around as PRO for China, and then I was in Korea, and that really broadened my horizons. When Red Cross, to use a current word, downsized,
I no longer had a job. I got a job editing a little magazine for the armed forces for two years. During that time I read a lot the section in which this magazine was also was part of the armed forces college so I took classes in the armed forces college
because I realized I didn't want to go back to Brownsville with just a junior college education, it wasn't anything for me to do that I would want to do. So I took a gamble and came to UT and I got the bachelor's and found that, of course, I was much better read than most of my fellow students.
After all, I was 35 years old, I was older than most graduate students as far as it went, so I did very well. I got what I had wanted at the time, an education, because it's necessary if you're going to really-- Let's put it in [inaudible] terms, to have a good income. [laughs]
Yes, the word heritage is synonymous with your work as a folklorist, as an activist.
Pardon?
The word heritage is synonymous with you, Dr. Paredes, as a folklorist, as an activist, as a scholar. Why is one's heritage so important?
That comes back to my early days when I used to listen to the old man talk and then I would spend three months over there, and then I would come, and take history, which told us a completely different view. I remember arguing with my teacher about the Monroe doctrine, some of those things
I got in there, because she felt that it was something very good for Latin America. I told her no, and she totally was-- I have it verbatim in the novel, she said, "What if you have a situation in which there's a little boy with candy and then a big boy comes
and tries to take the candy away from him, then another big boy comes and pushes the big boy away?" I said, "Yes, but then the other big boy takes the candy away from the little boy," and of course she allowed those things.
What we knew in our hearts from what our elders told us was different, that our heritage was not being given the respect that it deserved. What I did in The Herald during the Charro Days was milder, showing this song, for example, most Anglos I knew thought
that Sobre Las Olas was a German waltz, they knew it as Over The Waves. I wrote an article about Juventino Rosas and now he had written it and a number of other songs, so those things. But, more important to me was to try show what had been done, the injustices that have been done to our people,
and the value of our heritage. Much of that fell on deaf ears until I finally was able to come here and first I had almost forgotten the Nahuatl so what I did was with With His Pistol in His Hand was do the same job from a non-fiction viewpoint and using Gregorio Cortéz as a major figure in it.
I was not the only one on that, there were people working on that, even the LULAC at the time it was very timid, very assimilationist, yet they would come out once in a while. One of my younger brothers, Eleazar, he's dead now, he took a course-- And that was later, I never had that happen to me,
where he was told that, rather a textbook, said that Mexicans lived under trees and he had a big fight with the teacher, and he was expelled from school. One of my older brother went to see the LULAC people and they straightened the matter out, so that was happening all along.
The thing was that most of what our people knew was in corridos and in legends, in oral history, and I wanted to bring those things to the majority because I felt there were enough people of good will among the Anglos who if they saw our side they would really react. In a talk I gave
at Sacramento state after George Sánchez died, there was an activist. I made that point because Edward Simmons who did do a great deal, he was one of those that awakened, did say in his book The Chicano: From Caricature to Self-Portrait he says, "The lazy bandido sleeping
against the adobe wall finally has awakened," and I challenged him on that saying that we had been awake. People had been writing in Spanish mostly, that was the problem, so few of our elders knew English. They'd been writing, another one was Alonso Perales, En defensa de mi raza,
and they had been organizing and very often being put down, sometimes violently because of that. What I said there was the people that had awakened to a new ear were the Anglos because it was about that time that Anglos of good will began to see our side and we needed their help
to be able to make ourselves heard. That's why this story "The Hammon and the Beans" got published by an Anglo of good will, Ronnie Dugger, after a lot of Anglos refused to see that there was anything in it. We were lucky in a sense, I was, the English department has always been liberal, and Texas-
and they were willing to listen to me and even to allow me to get a PhD in English which was written about a ballad in Spanish about a historical figure. Chicanos very often don't know where to place me, whether to say I'm a historian, or I'm an anthropologist, or a literary figure,
but With His Pistol in His Hand had all of those things. I don't think I could have done that, at that time in the '50s, at any other department. Perhaps in anthropology because the anthropology have always been-- I didn't even know the anthropology department existed at that time.
What kind of comments can you make to children about their abuelitos and abuelitas? Why is it so important for children to still communicate with them? Sometimes you know in modern times with so much technology we forget where part of our history is, and part of our history is in our family.
Why is it so important for them to communicate?
One of my dreams, I never fulfilled it, though there's some people that were working on it, Tony, and do you know Joe Graham?
Yes, very well, we worked together.
Yes, he got his- [video cuts to black]
- our people put documents, things they had written, books they had read, all of those things went to the castaña and I wanted my students to go and talk to their abuelitos and abuelitas, to see about what they had, and to give them to their teachers who were interested in this sort of thing,
and that has been done to some extent. Not only does it further the knowledge our people but it gives the student self-esteem, to know that just because their grandparents don't know much English, or don't know any English at all, that they're dumb.
They probably were writing décimas, or other kind of poetry, and nobody knows about it, so that I think going back to one's roots is very important.
You founded the Mexican-American Studies Department here?
Yes.
How did you feel when you became the first one that ever creates such a department?
There we had a lot of problems. They tried. We had a Dean here who was supposed to be a liberal, the only liberal thing about him was that that he hated Frank Erwin who was a member of the Board of Regents, his name was--
John Silber.
Silber, old long John Silver they called him. [laughter] He was a short man.
[laughs] Carajo.
He was a son of a bitch. [laughs]
No doubt about it, he was as racist as he could be but most of the Anglo people thought he was a liberal. After all, he was locking horns with Frank Irwin, and Frank Irwin was no raging liberal himself, obviously. He tried to hamstring this thing by pitting the blacks against us. He took charge
because he scared the administration by telling that if we didn't have an ethnic studies program immediately they would be burning in the streets, and so on. He took charge and he established a program of ethnic studies, not Mexican-American studies, not Black studies,
and he got a retired, old retired professor, a black professor to run it. Of course, he thought that he had been given the job of setting up Black studies, so I had to clash with him. For example, he wanted the program to have Swahili, all students had to learn Swahili, but Swahili was never
an African language, it was a lengua franca that the Arabs developed when they were doing slaving expeditions in east Africa. He opposed my wanting to have Spanish--[Video cuts to black]